[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
support for this episode comes from
single store scaling modern sas is hard
it's even harder when you're using
databases that were built the last time
boy bands and low rise jeans were all
the rage single store is a modern cloud
database built for today's data
intensive applications and the smart sas
generation single store powers the new
wave of sas technologies displacing
legacy providers used to break the data
bottleneck and reduce your monthly cloud
bill in the process learn how single
store can help you at singlestore.com
se radio
hello everyone this is your host kanchan
shrinky welcome to software engineering
radio today our guest is wenki
naganathan
wenke is senior director of engineering
at konga he specializes in artificial
intelligence and chatbots in the last
two years wenki has led the aptis now
conga max ai mobile assistant for codes
and contracts from a cool new lab
concept to a live product
max is a siri google assistant and
alexa-like ai powered intelligence
platform that acts as a personal
assistant for sales and marketing
personnel
prior to conga wengki was director of
engineering ai platform services at
247.ai
welcome wenky really looking forward to
our conversation today is there anything
else you'd like to add to your bio
um no that looks great i'm looking
forward to our chat thank you
let's jump in with a very basic question
what was the need for this new
conversational ai for your b2b app and
why now
so i think of traditional user
interfaces as
something that's more suitable for
use cases that we can anticipate in
advance for example if you're building a
banking website
your traditional user interface is good
for
users logging in and retrieving your
basic account information and
transaction history but i'm sure
your application is capable of
delivering
you know a far more diverse set of
information at much
greater depth for instance if the user
has questions like
what's my average daily balance how many
atm transactions have performed in the
last month
unless the user interface has these
options there's no way for the user to
retrieve this information chatbots help
collapse the complexity of your user
interfaces and deliver
far more information using a much
simpler ux so that's essentially how i
view chatbots and virtual assistants for
most applications
and also if you look at it from a
historical perspective
virtual assistant is basically a natural
evolution of user interfaces at one
point
used to live on command line interfaces
and then they became guise and then they
got subsumed into their web interface
and and then soon it was on mobile and
nowadays applications are becoming more
complex so users are becoming more
demanding so to address all of the use
cases and deliver an optimal ux
we gotta you know mix traditional user
interfaces with you know non-traditional
ones like nl
that's where it fits in
so why is it taking off now though was
this need not felt earlier or is it just
that we have the technology at this time
yeah we certainly the rays of siri alexa
google assistant-like uh platforms have
you know popularized this right a lot of
users are beginning to use it and
they consider it useful
and also the technology has evolved to a
point where
building such technology such interfaces
in a credible manner as possible now
tell us a little bit more about max
you know you certainly alluded to the
fact that the technological evolution
helped that and there was a business
need too but maybe you can tell us a
little bit more about the business
aspects as well
yeah so first of all max is uh like you
said it's a silly alexa google assistant
like uh virtual assistant it's capable
of workflow automation
skill automation and also it's capable
of many other things which i'll talk
about as we go on
there are a couple of reasons why
we really built max first is the
business need
and second is
we also saw an interesting industry
trend
so on the business need before i talk
about it i need to give you a little bit
more context about what we do at kanga
at kanga we build
software applications that help our
customers run their revenue operations
our typical
end user is a enterprise salesperson
they're not the only persona but they're
the typical persona for our
products
and the typical use case is a sales
person taking
a pre-sales opportunity all the way
through sales demand quotation process
to
turning that into a contract
and managing the redlining process and
turning and getting that signed and
managing the life cycle of contracts
turning all of that into cache etc so
this is the code to cache domain
and workflows in this domain tend to be
really complex so we needed a tool or an
engine
that can simplify user experience and
improve productivity in this domain
right so that's the genesis of max and
second
on the industry trend
not too long ago when steve jobs
introduced the iphone probably about a
decade and a half or so ago
blackberry used used to be the dominant
brand in the enterprise right today
you don't see blackberries it has been
completely replaced by smartphones
similarly
once upon a time we used to make phone
calls to our colleagues to collaborate
today we use messaging right so these
are all examples of
strong consumer trends pushing an income
and trend out you know and making their
way into the enterprise so we see a
similar thing happening with
chat bots right so the advent of siri
alexa google assistant like you said
have uh you know improved user
experience in the world of in in the
consumer world and we think that
it's just a matter of time before they
find their way into the enterprise so
it's still very early stages but it's
going to happen
so those are really the drivers for max
can we take an example of a question
that max has asked and then talk about
what distinguishes max from the others
yeah so you can ask
max to automate a workflow or create a
workflow for example you can tell max to
create an nda for google and send it to
conscient for signature so
max will automatically figure out all of
the details involved in orchestrating
the workflow and accomplish that it's
like your virtual secretary or you can
tell max to
pull up information that satisfies a
particular criteria right for for
instance you can tell max to look up all
the msas that are over twenty thousand
dollars
from last year that are said to expire
this quarter and max will understand the
nuances in the sentence and pull up the
exact information max is also capable of
providing you just in time notification
of important events that happen in the
system it behaves exactly like a
you know
very intelligent human secretary right
constantly remaining their bosses
of what needs to be done and also
helping the masses you know be
productive in terms of differences
between max and the conventional mods
that you see out there so
first let me
talk about google assistant alexa and
and siri
they are more encyclopedic in nature
they
go
you know a lot broader they try to
address
all possible questions
but they are a little shallow right you
can ask them
things like how's the weather in san
francisco or
when is the thanksgiving next year
typically they answer one or two
questions and
that's the you know scope of those uh
you know assistance uh you can still go
deeper you can build vertical skills
with alexa for instance if you do that
you will end up creating an application
like max
max is more comparable to
the assistance that you see on travel
websites and retail websites and so on
it's purposeful for a particular domain
to serve use cases in the domain well
right
one of the
things that we did before we built max
is you know did an exhaustive research
of what's out there to understand how
how to build max and what we found is
majority of the bots in these travel
websites and retail websites
they over promise and under deliver they
are usually very rigid and rugged what
that means is
they are they
they they just
chatbot like interfaces but they behave
like traditional menus right
you pretty much have to do what they
expect you to do if you wear of course
then
you're going to end up with a
sub-optimal user experience and
typically users notice that quickly and
disengage right away which is why these
bots don't work
so max is built
like a google google maps
for an uh so what that means is
it helps the user and guides the user
and and stays with the user and helps
the user get to where they want
but if the user wears of course it stays
with the user and still continues to
help the user right
and as i talk a little bit about the
nuances of how to
what what goes into this and how to
build this you will understand the
capabilities that we have thought about
and you know developed
so will will max coexist with your uh
web and mobile ux or you know over time
do you expect it to take over more and
more of that
i see that as a supplementary interface
to uh what exists right you cannot uh
chat bots won't work out because they're
exciting this is a common misconception
that people have oh i built this cool
new thing everybody is going to start
using it and so on first of all
you have to think of them as a tool to
improve productivity in specific context
right also for them to be successful
they have to do skill automation it
cannot just be that it saved 14 clicks
that's not why people use
a tool right
so more generally speaking if you rewind
to maybe
15 years ago 20 years ago
when you called an airline you would
have heard oh welcome to xyz airline
press one for english two for spanish
and then when you press one
you heard one for flight status two for
reservations etcetera there were these
hierarchy of menus
and then each menu had nested menus and
then it led to more nested menus and the
the complexity of the ui was just
through the roof
and if you make a single mistake you're
probably going to start all over again
right it made for a really frustrating
user experience so think about how the
same menus are delivered today right
today
it asks you
what do you want right if you want to
check for flight status it pretty much
takes you there right away right
so that's a classic example of how
people have used virtual assistants to
simplify the user experience
and in the in the case of max i talked
about creating an nda and sending it to
somebody for signature
that is a little bit of skill involved
in creating an indie you need to choose
the right templates and document format
and you need to understand
a little bit illegal and
also you need to know that you know your
company processes to send it to somebody
for signature and get it all done so
here there is an opportunity for us to
do skill automation right so by by just
giving a simple command you have a tool
that behaves like a secretary and
accomplishes exactly what you want
and in addition
you can think of these virtual
assistants as
something that can you know help you
access information on the go if you're
on your mobile in an airport you can
access information quickly
uh you can get a reminder notifications
and take follow-up actions on them
etc so these are all the different
scenarios where
we think these bots are virtual
assistants will be useful
i don't think of them as interfaces that
can completely you know replace the
traditional interfaces that are out
there because
traditional interfaces are still very
valuable if you are doing something
really lengthy and tedious think about
creating a coach with 10 000 line items
there's no way you're going to do that
effectively with the bot right it's you
would much rather have a external
spreadsheet like tool where you have
complete visibility and control of
everything that you want and
and it gives you the flexibility to go
and tweak anything you want so the
traditional interfaces are still going
to be there and i see bots and virtual
assistants as an opportunity to
supplement those user interfaces in a
targeted manner and make that make it a
lot more
useful and productive for the end users
so my takeaway from what we've talked so
far
is that this new assistant is purpose
built it has to be
conversational really conversational not
rule-based and capable of deep
conversation handling follow-up
questions
given that can we now discuss what does
it take to build an assistant like this
absolutely i think there are
four major pieces that go into building
a virtual assistant a really good
virtual assistant
so let me talk through them a bit
first is the user interface you know the
second one is the
nlu engine with all of the capabilities
that you need to build a sophisticated
virtual assistant and then the third
piece is a dialog orchestrator this is
the
you can think of it like your little
operating system for running your bot
application
and then finally your actual bot
application that runs through your use
cases or workflows right
so
let's start with the
user interface
so you need to think about how do you
place uh where do you place the part how
do you surface the bot right typically
bots don't exist in vacuum it's very
rare for bot to be the only application
that delivers
all of the user experiences that you
want to deliver typically they coexist
in is part of a larger ecosystem so
typically people put these virtual
assistants on their websites it's pretty
straightforward
interface you just have a a way to
launch your bot application on your
website and then you can
engage with the user using either why is
it text typically it's text
or you can uh surface your
bot application as part of your ivrs
right like you've seen with all the
airline
companies
you may already have an ivr in which
case you just attach your bot to the
driver you'll build a little ivr app and
attach it to your existing system
or you could have you could consider
placing your bot in social channels
if you already have
an existing channel on facebook
messenger or you know
whatsapp or one of these social channels
you could consider placing your bot
there
as part of that ecosystem
or
you could you know consider placing this
in a mobile app if you already have one
right in the absence of any of these
alternatives
you want to think about surfacing the
bot or meeting the user where the user
already lives as opposed to
dragging the user to your own app right
this is a classic a lot of people think
oh i need to build a mobile app to
deliver this right
so what you want to think about is um if
you take your
i have an iphone 12 and i have
24 apps on my home screen right and how
many of them do i really launch on a
daily basis maybe one or two
and then there are three or four pages
of these apps i very rarely are never
launched
an app on the third or fourth page right
so if you're going to pour in a lot of r
d dollars to build an application you
make sure that it is going to be useful
for an end user and they're going to use
it on a daily basis
otherwise you may consider placing
your bot in existing channels so we
build
for users who live in the enterprise and
they already use tools like slack and
team so we we thought it is more
appropriate for this to be
you know this our max to live in those
ecosystems right so
max can be accessed via slack and themes
so that makes it uh easier for us to you
know solve
you know user option problems and so on
and it reduces the friction so that's
the first decision you need to make
right and once you've decided uh how
where you want to surface it you build
the appropriate ui integrations and
and build the appropriate ui widgets to
surface your
output or as well as solicit the input
then comes the nlu capabilities so here
typically you will have to make a viable
decision
so
if you unless you're trying to
distinguish your technology on nl itself
which is pretty rare or you are
operating at such mind numbing scale
that the economics wouldn't work out for
you
you probably want to consider buying
this technology there are a lot of good
ones out there
so nlu meaning natural language
understanding and as you're talking
maybe you can also distinguish that from
nlp or natural language processing
sure
so yeah uh let me talk through the
components and then we'll talk about nlp
and luml et cetera then maybe
so i was talking about the
potential buy is built in nlu and i was
recommending more pi because there are
pretty good technologies out there there
is microsoft luis ibm mats and google
dialog flow then many more that you can
consider
so in so nlu helps you take user inputs
process them understand the uh the
semantics of what is being spoken
so you uh know what to process or how to
process it right in addition to
the nlu engine that i
suggested buying
you probably need to augment that with
your own you know domain specific nl
handling
for example in the case of max we had to
build
a stack of nl technologies
and parsers that understood business
speak currencies timelines
so our users can say things like
pull up codes that are
set the end date of this code to
first work day of the third quarter of
fi 2021 this is a complex
timeline expression right
in order for us to process this
correctly we need to translate these
types of expressions to accurate dates
so so in addition to the you know
generic anal handling that understands
the semantics you also
need to solve these uh vertical or
domain specific nl expressions so you
typically you will end up building on
top of the
anal engine that you use so that's the
nlp so once you've received the input
processing input understood the
semantics process all of these complex
business speaks
now you have all of the information
organized to process this and take it to
the next step and then comes uh
your application level processing right
here you need to think about do you need
to build any further infrastructure
in order for you to process this for
example we had to solve this
natural language sql translation problem
for us to accurately take
the
the information that the user spoke to
the actual queries that can you know be
run on the database and and the
appropriate results produced
so that's again a a part of your annual
ecosystem that
you need to build right okay so that's
the nl part the third is the dialogue
orchestrator so i would uh describe this
as a mini operating system like
capability to host your bot application
right so once you understand what the
user said you need to
hand it over to a part right you need to
initialize the part you need to provide
the space for the bot to execute another
container type
infrastructure to execute you need to
initialize the state of the bot and then
as the bot executes step by step you
need to stay with the bot help the bot
execute all of these steps and then when
the bot produces an output you need to
hand it back to the user interface and
then you need to swap the bot out and
persist all of its state right
and
multiple bots could exist in this
ecosystem potentially right so that's
what this dialogue orchestrator does now
is this a buyer a bull
well if you are building
a one-off bot one or two bots
you can consider
purchasing this capability as part of
the core nlu engine itself because some
of the
anal vendors try to solve this for you
but usually they are very limited but if
you're building something generic and
you're going to build hundreds of bots
then you may want to consider building
your own dialogue orchestrator because
that gives you a lot of flexibility
and then finally
you have your bot application now the
bot application
is the one that actually you know
understands the user input and executes
the use case and produces results
right so here
there are a lot of best practice
considerations that you may want to
think about
first is when a bot is launched
you probably need to offer the user some
kind of a menu or a customer's welcome
screen
that invites the user to engage in
productive conversations it helps the
user understand what are the
possibilities
and then as the user moves along you
want to offer the user proactive tips
right so if the user pulls up accounts
you want to tell the user what they can
do with these accounts because
unlike traditional user interfaces it's
not very intuitive what the bots can do
right and
bots can potentially have infinite
capabilities how does the user discover
these capabilities so you need to
help the user understand this wherever
possible without being too invasive and
you also want to offer users help that
are that is context sensitive so if the
user is viewing some information the
user is looking at the payment options
and asking for help
you want to offer help related to
payment options and also
the other thing that
is important to consider is topic
switches
so as humans we tend to switch
topics right that's how we think if
you're asked a question
you typically answer a counter question
in order for you to uncover the answer
to the previous question that's how we
think
bots do not understand it if the bots
are rigid and they don't allow the user
to ask these questions they'll be pretty
limited and not very useful so it's kind
of like a little subroutine call from
your main routine if you're a programmer
right allow the user to do the topics
which go
you know explore this new world and then
help them come back
navigation controls is the other
consideration so this is a constant
source of frustration for users
bots often
take the user down a path and then box
the user into that little uh space and
the user cannot come out of it this
makes for a really frustrating user
experience user may have
by mistake gone there because the user
doesn't know what exists there but you
need to allow the user to come back
right go back to the step three go back
to the previous step
let's go get back to payments right so
users should have the ability to
navigate the part from wherever it is
and
bonus points for handling graceful
endings so usually users say thank you
and then it's good to say you're welcome
as opposed to meeting that with silence
and then sometimes users
don't necessarily ask the questions that
you are anticipating right users may
have a related question but still a
relevant question right if i'm going to
a best buy you know website
and the bot let's say i can handle
questions about tvs and you know you
know dvrs
i may have a question about the store
location right where is the nearest
store next to my home right
and if the bot cannot answer that then
it doesn't help me
so being able to handle
related questions that are still like
valid questions just
goes a long way in establishing that
trust and credibility with the user
and
the other capabilities that we should
consider building are
some sort of mechanism for the user to
provide feedback
because
you don't want to assume that your part
works perfectly and produces good
results one of that's one of the
challenges
when a user asks something you produce
something
you don't know
in software whether you produce the
right output or not it's a user who's
going to judge that and
give the user an opportunity to provide
feedback and listen to this feedback and
learn
handle chatbot lingos if you can because
these days uh terms like brb and
ttl kind of uh
phrases are you know pretty common
that's what users use in other chat
tools and they tend to do the same thing
with your bot so understand those things
handle profanity unfortunately no matter
how good a bot is sometimes it can make
for a frustrating user experience and
this can usually cause users to swear at
the bot so be prepared to handle that
and use analytics to track the usage of
your bot
uh track the performance of your part
and then pay attention to this data and
then keep refining about so these are
basically the characteristics of a bot
application so overall uh to summarize
you need to think about where to place
your bot in the user interface and how
best to deliver this
and then second you need to think about
the nl capabilities that you want to
have
then you need to think about a dialogue
orchestrator and then finally
you want to think about
you know the actual
details of the bot application itself so
those are the pieces that go into
building a really good and powerful part
that makes the end user productive
so couple of follow-up questions on that
you mentioned there could be hundreds of
parts you know at least several so what
is the scope of
a bot typically in this context
and
i assume you know certainly there are
multiple conversations going on so there
must be some
work to manage the state across these as
well so can you just comment on these
two things
yeah so if you're a b2b vendor and
building bots for multiple businesses
each bot could be a
part that serves a different you know
tenant or even within the same tenant
you can have
a payment journey you can have a faq
journey you can have a account access
and cancellation you can have you know
if
so say if you're in an airline business
it could be a flight status bar it could
be a
reservation spot it could be a mileage
account access part and so on so
these bots could be totally independent
or they could play with each other so
all of those are possibilities right so
how these spots actually interact with
each other the details of that is within
the bot applications but dialogue
orchestrator will offer that
infrastructural piece
for you to build these uh you know bots
that can interplay with each other more
effective thanks for that winky let's
now drill deep into nlp nlu and also
where machine learning and deep learning
would fit here
absolutely so all of them are
kind of related so i think of this as
okay think of artificial intelligence as
a superset and then machine learning is
a part of that and
and nlp and nlu is part of machine
learning and so is deep learning right
so let's talk about them one at a time
so nlp and nlu are close cousins right
you can think of that as overlapping
subset or your you can think of that as
one within the other
so nlp is basically a set of techniques
to take user input process it prepare it
for next steps
so when you say i'm running 100 meters
in the olympics
there are a lot of words in that
sentence i am running 100 meters in the
olympics so
nlp tries to tokenize your input and
split it into tokens
then it does stop word removal to remove
unnecessary words
it does something called you know root
word identification by doing something
called stemming and limitization so in
the case of running running is not as
interesting as the word run run is
really the root word
so it does all of this preparation to
ensure that the subsequent steps can be
more easily performed so that's
essentially what nlp tries to do right
nlu is understanding the semantics of
what these utterances like
what is the user really trying to say
what is the intent behind the statement
for example when the user says
pull up contracts over 20k from last
year that are set to expense here
users simply wanted to
you know look up the
contracts or agreement records
that is the intent and there are several
parameters to this intent 20k or 20k
from last year
expire
next year these are various parameters
for this you know sentence so nlu tries
to understand
the parameters for
the intent and then in some cases you
probably want to understand the
sentiment and so on in in other cases it
may be more
so this is essentially what nlu tries to
do right and nlp captures works with the
syntax and
and the preprocessing and then nlu works
with the semantics
right now let's switch to
machine learning
now all of this is part of machine
learning only
but
not for us to understand machine
learning it's important to understand
how the world could be without machine
learning right if you were to
take a bunch of user utterances and then
try to guess what the user is trying to
say
you probably want to write a whole bunch
of rules to understand okay if the word
has some lookup action
sorry if the sentence has some lookup
action and it refers to an object like
contracts and it refers to some
parameters
user is probably talking about looking
up contracts right
but
contracts may not be the only word user
i may use user may use many other words
to describe contracts agreements would
be a way to describe contracts right so
you quote all of these rules in your
application to understand okay
if this is the case if this is the case
if this is the case
then user is trying to look up the
contracts and then that you will
probably notice some exceptions to these
rules
user may combine multiple objects in one
sentence so your your rules based in a
code
is not adequate to handle that so you
will code more rules more rules more
rules so one thing that is guaranteed to
happen with rules based programming is
your rules is going to keep on growing
and at some point your rules may
conflict with each other in which case
you need to quote exception rules and so
on so this makes your program very
complex and
rules is something only an expert
programmer can write right
a non-expert programmer a non-expert
user cannot build these rules
so that makes the application really
hard to book
machine learning basically turns this
paradigm on its head
why do we have to write these tools is
that a way for us to synthesize these
rules automatically
so in that case how do you synthesize
the rules so so machine learning is
basically an art of
writing a program that
takes
training examples
and then tries to automatically build
these rules right so if you're trying to
recognize an image the training examples
could be okay this image is a cat this
image is a dog this image is some other
animal and so on and the machine
learning algorithm tries to understand
the input and your labels and tries to
make an association
okay i found these things and the user
said this is actually a cat so i think
these four things could mean cat
so it can still lead to ridiculous
rules building so that's where your
training examples have to be adequate
otherwise
garbage in garbage out
so with this type of programming
paradigm
it's easy for us to
um scale your
rule set right by by providing more and
more training examples so this is
something a non-expert
user can do right training is something
that a business analyst can do and
that makes it easier for you to build
your app and data is something that
you're going to constantly keep getting
right as more users interact with your
system and it may be even possible to
automate this training to a degree so
your algorithm gets smarter and smarter
so that is machine learning now on to
deep learning now
machine learning is good
and powerful
but it doesn't keep on getting smarter
as you add more data which is what you
want right beyond a point the
smartness of the you know the algorithm
saturates
so that's where deep learning comes in
so deep learning is in some ways an old
wine and a new bottle it used to be
popular in the 90s it's based on neural
networks
so there is there are layers and layers
of neural networks each layer processes
information sends it to the next layer
and so on and so forth and until the
real output comes out that's essentially
how deep learning systems work
deep learning has become popular now
because back in the 90s we didn't have
the processing capabilities too
first of all we didn't have access to
all of this data that we have access to
now
on top of it we didn't have the
capability to process all of this big
data we didn't have the you know
computing power etc to do that now we
have all of that so deep learning
algorithms have come back
now deep learning works better than
machine learning because
they can get smarter as you add more and
more data and we have access to all of
that data now
and it also has some properties like
transfer learning it can learn things
from one context and take that to the
other context right so basically you can
build models that
i've i've been trained to understand the
english language and then you can do
some fine tuning of these models to
understand how to read english contracts
and it also has the ability to
self-select features so as travis is
through the neural net it can highlight
or suppress features
that are important or unimportant so all
of these properties make deep learning
really interesting and deep learning
obviously is a lot more complex
science than machine learning so yeah
that's the difference between
our sponsor for this episode is spot by
netapp spot provides a comprehensive
suite of cloud ops tools that make it
easy to deliver continuously optimized
and reliable infrastructure at the
lowest possible cost imagine automating
your infrastructure to proactively meet
the needs of your applications imagine
leveraging the latest in machine
learning and automation to scale your
infrastructure using the most efficient
mix of instances and pricing models
eliminating the risks of
over-provisioning and expensive lock-in
from cost management to infrastructure
automation and cd to running serverless
spark on kubernetes spot ensures you
maximize your cloud investment the end
result is simply more cloud at less cost
discover how the most innovative
companies from cloud native growth
machines to forward-thinking enterprises
are automating simplifying and
optimizing their cloud infrastructures
with spot by netapp
check them out at spot.io
se radio where you can find more
information request a demo or give a try
by starting a free trial
so i've heard of what to wag and bert b
ert in this context could you elaborate
on these
sure so word to work is basically a
technique to
transform words to numbers so it's
important to do that because we need a
mathematical model to work with words
computer needs a mathematical model to
work with words
once you have that mathematical model
you can start you know performing word
arithmetic comparisons of words
uh one of the most celebrated examples
here is uh
birthday models can be used to compare
let's say if you said man to woman is
same as king two and then word to a
model
can say king to queen i can associate
meanings like uh
oh or rather it can understand that
sweden is more closer to norway than uh
more closer to us right so all of this
is pretty much learnt on in an
unsupervised manner you can
read pages and pages of text once it's
transformed to some mathematical model
it can make all of these associations
pretty much uh on its own uh without any
human intervention and people have built
interesting models on top of this uh
are are using this principle
by embedding more and more contextual
meanings by taking words and
you know mapping them to multiple vector
forms and using those models
you can do lots of interesting things
examples of models that work this way
are bert and gpt2 and gp3 people have
built models
that with gpd3 that can read pages of
text
and practically answer questions on that
based on the text like a human would
with no additional training so that
makes it really interesting so it won't
be in the scope of a conversation today
to go deeper into birth or what to wake
but it would be great if you can point
our listeners to any reading material
out there
yeah so if you're a casual user um or
reader you can google your way to a lot
of this information but if you're a
little bit more serious
there are youtube lectures youtube
stanford lectures that you can listen to
are if you want to do something more
specialized there are course at our
courses by andrew hang
very comprehensive machine learning and
deep learning courses are offered there
that is udemy courses so you can do all
of this
or if you're really really serious about
you know having a carrier in this space
i mean you need to actually build some
applications to
you know understand these technologies
in more detail
so we'll check with you uh weenke and
put some of you know key links that you
found useful in our show notes
absolutely
let's now talk a little bit about other
b2b problems that could be solved with
this infrastructure
you know have you encountered any of
these
yeah so there are lots of problems we
can solve with good nlp nlu capabilities
so
chatbots is one immediate application
we've talked about it at length if you
in the world of you know
contracts there are a lot of interesting
problems that you can solve
in this domain
for example so many times we receive uh
you know different contracts by mail
your home warranty contracts your
verizon contract it's like 15 pages in
size and you never read through them
because it's a lot of legal language
it'll be nice if somebody can summarize
to you
the four or five bullet points that you
care about things like what is my annual
payment or monthly payment
what is my early termination penalty and
what if i move to a different city
what if i want to change my telephone
number that sort of thing right so
being able to read a contract provide
critique on the contract providing a
summary of the contract is is a useful
problem to solve
being able to have some kind of a best
practice
template and being able to semantically
diff it would be another uh interesting
problem to solve being able to
understand read the contract and
understanding the different risks in it
would be another problem to solve and so
on this is just the world of contracts
so if you are you you have used
zoom meetings right zoom meeting now has
this
live transcript right so the live
transcript uh not the live transcript
but rather the transcript of the meeting
that you are in
so that's another nlp problem and also
auto summarization of your conference
call would be another interesting
problem right if you were on the call
for two hours what's the summary right
so these are all various problems that
are really interesting to to look at i
think some companies are already
beginning to solve them but it hasn't
become mainstream yet
let's switch gears a little bit and talk
about the data you know these bots and
conversational interfaces that we have
been talking about are very focused on
the domain so what about the data for
training
yeah so
you definitely need
domain specific data for them to be
meaningfully trained you need to work
with domain experts so in the case of
contracts you probably need legal
operations people right you probably
need to hire lawyers to train and build
these models
so it's a it's going to be a combination
of
using their expertise and also there is
a lot of rich data out there on the
internet so if you just need public
domain contracts there are probably
thousands of them millions of them
so you can download the from these data
sets and use that as well but you're
also going to learn a lot from your
customer data but this is a sensitive
subject
because customers need to opt in and
allow you to use that data
and our hope is that this industry is
going to evolve somewhat like how
the music industry evolved when napster
came along and said i'm gonna
publish all the music on online that was
huge resistance in the industry to go in
that direction
but 20 years later i'll pretty much all
of the music is consumed online so
we think eventually uh customers will be
more open to the thought of sharing that
information for the you know for their
own good and for the you know goodness
of the entire community so yeah using a
combination of homegrown
the public domain data as well as your
customer data you can build your models
and make them smarter
how does testing fit in
yeah testing is a little tricky here
because this is not conventional
software where you've written
requirements and then you code it to
those requirements and
and you can just test through the
requirements because if you build a
wizard like screen and conventional
software unless there is a next button
you cannot click on it and go to the
next screen but this is a chat bot so
anybody can say anything at any point in
time so the testing is somewhat
unconventional you still need your
regular automated unit testing and your
regression testing and your you know
regular functional testing and all the
performance testing and all of that but
in addition uh
to ensure that what you've built is
functionally complete and it makes sense
for an end user you need to put it
through some kind of a crowdsource
alpha testing you need to engage users
across
different teams
if you have a sales team and marketing
team willing to participate in this
testing you know invite them engage them
and get feedback from them if you have
talk if you're targeting consumer
audience you can you know test it with a
focus group to understand whether your
application is working or not so once
you have a deployment of
your app then you have a lot of data
from your customer usage and from that
you can get
meaningful you know insights and
understanding of how this is going to be
used so typically when you introduce
some new feature yeah you want to run it
through some kind of a trial process
to ensure that this is going to work
so you also said that once the product
is being used by customers that's
additional feedback
is that data also used for further
training
yeah
absolutely so here you probably need to
declare to the declare or disclose to
the customer that you're planning on
doing that and it's pretty much part of
your software agreements after licensing
agreement
but in some cases customers may
may want may be okay with using certain
data may not be okay with using some
data so in that case it becomes a little
bit more complex
you
need to then start anonymizing the data
masking important pieces of information
right that are not significant for your
model because your model probably
doesn't need to know that
the value of a contract is twenty
thousand dollars it probably cares about
other aspects of the contract right so
in that case you can try and solve the
problem that way but some cases
customers may be extremely sensitive and
say i don't want you to touch my data at
all i want you to just
i know use it for processing and nothing
else in that case you pretty much have
to honor what the customer is saying and
and not you know use the data for any
other training
in terms of training and testing and the
whole life cycle
what about localization so if you have
you know if you're done with english and
you want to now move on to spanish what
does that mean
so this is a lot more complex topic
because
you need to start with your language
models right so you need a language
agnostic model first of all
and you need to be able to
and if you've written all of these
business speak layers right which you've
probably written for english you need to
write them rewrite them or adapt them
for different languages so that's a big
complex piece of work
and then as you run through your part
and bot produces output you need to
tailor the output in
the appropriate language i think
the localization as in presenting the
output in a particular language that's
probably the easier part of the problem
the harder parts of the problem are
understanding what the user is doing
doing nlu and nlp and nlu for your
languages and then doing all of the
added layers the domain specific and
layers in the specific language that's
where the complexity is
we did
talk about the q a part and the dialog
orchestrator
what about actions what are the
additional integrations needed to
perform actions maybe there's a
integration with the notification
service is there does that make sense is
there something else that you need to
build for that i mean your actions are
going to depend on what type of workload
is your action could very well be
if they are asking for information on
something or account information you you
can very well dip into your crm system
and lift that information
or your action could be like
if you're turning on a heater system you
need to externally interface with some
nest or some thermostat to turn that on
or it could
even be user asking hey
send me reminder notifications about uh
some something that's happening in the
system so speaking of notifications
which seems like the
essence of your question yes i think uh
you'd see it may seem like mobile
notifications in chatbot are somewhat
orthogonal but
they have an opportunity to coexist and
deliver a um you know a pretty good set
of use cases so
we in max we have
integrated these things very closely we
send a combination of reminder
notifications and just-in-time
notifications and then users can take
follow-up actions on these notifications
for example if you send an agreement for
approval
you want to notify the user who needs to
approve this agreement and right there
as part of the notification you provide
the user the option to do follow-ups and
then the user can do follow-ups and then
when the user takes follow-up actions it
notifies the
sender that you know
actions have been taken it's the ball is
on your code to do the next steps so
this helps us move workflows at the
speed of the user
uh and not be like bound or shackled by
technology so chatbots play an important
role in making all of this happen
so we talked about languages and now i'd
like to ask you about voice
did you integrate with voice
so why is this a very complex topic
so siri alexa they work as two-way voice
engines right they work like that
primarily because
they do they solve very simple problems
right
if you want to really build a good solid
b2b application otherwise what does it
take first you need a wireless
recognition engine
typically you would simply buy this
engines because there are a lot of good
ones out there but there are some unique
complexities that you will have to
handle right so you know in the world of
b2b if the customer says pull up the
cisco agreements that are
from last year right
what cisco
are you talking about are you talking
about cisco the networking company or
sysco the food distribution company
right
in text it's pretty clear which one it
is and why is it's not clear right that
is ambiguity in what is being spoken so
you probably need some dynamic
dictionary integration with your input
processing and then when you come back
with information uh if you are pulling
up a code there are like 15 line items
in a code how do you render this in
voice if it's like visual you can simply
show it user can scan it it makes
a lot of sense to the user if it's if it
has to be rendered and wise
how do you render this in a manner that
you know that helps the user consume all
of these details easily so in that case
you probably need to summarize the two
or three things you're missing
information that user may care about and
also you may have to pull state machines
to render the output itself
all of this makes
y somewhat less use two-way y somewhat
less useful but what may be more useful
is one way wise right you can use
siri alexa like dictate uh
like interfaces are even
uh your built-in mobile phone dictation
services to
inject your input and voice
right and then you can get back the
output and text right that way
you don't have to type
in your mobile which may be complex to
do with limited real estate
and limited keyboard capabilities
but you are able to
still effectively use it
and retrieve the information that you
are looking for so
so that's that's how we thought about
voice
it's more one-way wise than two-way
voice yeah
the last part of the platform section
um what would like to get a little bit
of insight into deployment
what were the additional components you
had to think of deploying and did they
change your basic framework in any way
and your pipelines
so when it comes to deployment you still
have the traditional software stack you
are running your microservices in a
container and you probably have a need
for your cloud infrastructure
like your radish and and or
whatever database that you're using
etc etc right so you still need to solve
all of the traditional deployment
problems so when it comes to deploying
nl-related stuff that is models right
there may be a base model and then there
may be customer specific models and then
even the base model may not be one thing
it may be a combination of things
you need tooling to deploy all of that
effectively and sometimes
you may be
you may not sure that a particular model
will function great so you probably need
to have infrastructure to do some kind
of an a b testing
so you deploy a newer version of a
particular model and you want to see how
that behaves
and you want to study that before you
roll it out to your general user base so
you need to probably have infrastructure
to do that type of rollout
and in addition yeah there may be
configurations and other things that you
may want to deploy as well so you need
tooling for a tooling and an
infrastructure for all of this
let's switch gears and not talk about
building the team
what is the makeup of a team that builds
this app
what skills sets are needed perhaps you
can talk about how you build a team
was a build and buy decision done before
or after
some information about the team would be
great
so bulldozes by is never straightforward
one not the other it's usually
almost always a hybrid in practically
all projects that i've been part of you
buy things where where you can
realize quick time to value and that's
not significant advantage in building or
the cost of building is very high
and you end up building a whole bunch of
things that nobody has solved for you
right so that's how i think about bios's
so it's it's usually a hybrid so in
terms of team skills it's going to be a
combination of
data scientists and traditional software
engineers and devops and user experience
experts
your traditional engineering managers
product managers etc right and then
if you
need to solve you know domain specific
problems right you may have to hire
domain specific experts or you can
contract them you can contract their
services the case of contracts you may
you may want to consider adding legal
personnel to your team right
because ux is a big part of this people
often underestimate how important ux is
to this
u.s is a very critical uh part of uh
building a good virtual assistant
because you need to blend your
traditional user interfaces with you
know chatbot interface
and unlike traditional interface where
user is already pre-trained
subconsciously to go look for things in
a certain manner there's no such thing
for chatbots so you need to figure out a
way to educate the user
without you know sounding too invasive
you cannot show like a very complex ui
with hundreds of knobs
for the user to learn about you need to
like
do that in a very subtle manner so ux
plays a big role in this and then uh
finally uh
like we had talked about earlier when it
comes to testing you need to crowdsource
the effort you need to involve multiple
people from different disciplines so you
you need to consider them as well as
part of the larger team that you're
trying to build to build these things
yeah thank you for answering the
question about the ux design that was
going to be a specific area i talked you
know i i drilled into further
a key example i have from my recent
experience is just that
if you don't do that you probably will
get up ending json
somewhere in your chat and that's a very
basic thing you don't want to do you
certainly want to format your responses
if nothing else
absolutely i think in addition let's say
you are serving users user wants to
order food in an airline right the
choices of food that you have is more
appropriately you know delivered as a
traditional user interface it's a card
right
that you can view so the user can view
the image of the food and then the price
the
the nutritional information etc right
how do you deliver all of this in chat
bots so it has to be a combination of
your traditional user interface with you
know the chatbot like stuff so
i mean this problem is fairly well
solved but yeah ux
helps you build these things very
creatively and
deliver a superior user user experience
to the user
so one of our listeners would like to
start a new company where conversational
interface or maybe just nlp nlu is at
the heart of the experience
how would you advise them to get started
so i would say start with your business
problem and think about how best to
deliver a solution to address your
business problem and then think about
all of the interfaces that you need to
deliver that value
and then think about how chatbots will
enhance that user experience don't start
with the notion that hey you need to
build a chatbot company that's not how
you should think about it
uh always start with the business
problem i think uh
once you do that you will have a clear
understanding of how chatbot fits into
the overall puzzle and enhances the
overall value of your product once you
do that and you you you understood what
use cases to deliver and how to deliver
these
then you can think about all of the
things we just talked about early on in
the segment right how to where to place
the ui and you know what nl engines to
choose
then do you want to build or buy your
dialogue orchestrator then how best to
build your bot etc all
are there any open source technologies
or
commercial technologies that you think
people should evaluate
yeah yeah there are tons in fact nobody
writes everything from scratch in this
domain right you typically leverage a
lot of open source work that has been
already done for you
and then you build on that so if you're
solving the traditional chatbot problem
that is microsoft lewis that is ibm
watson that is google dialog flow that
you can start with
you probably want to augment that with
your own proprietary algorithms and so
on
and then if you're solving different
kinds of nlp general purpose nlp
problems or contract language
understanding that type of thing
you can start with the language models
that has been built for you right bert
and
you know ulm fit and gpt2 and gpt3 and
so on and then see how you can adapt
these to solve the specific problems
that you are solving
thank you venky so starting to wind down
now
what other use cases or applications are
you thinking about for the platform
you've built beyond conversational ui
yeah so i talked about conversational ui
and alerting um in addition
it's a good uh you can think of it as a
search engine right
how do you search on google you pretty
much type things in natural language
right and then it brings back
information that you want so it's it's
an opportu it's a useful interface for a
search engine
and then
it can be a good document analyze
analysis tool so there are different
kinds of documentations that exist in
our world i talked a lot about contracts
so there are lots of different problems
you can solve with contracts like auto
summarization
semantic similarity and and many other
problems that we discussed early on
yeah those could be solved with
max-like technologies
is there anything we missed today that
you would like to cover
nothing in particular i think we pretty
much covered everything exhaustively i
mean i'm a humble little student in this
space and i have a lot to learn if you
got good bright productive ideas and you
want to reach out to me i'll be happy to
share whatever little i know and
happy to learn what you can offer me and
let's do that let's connect offline if
you want to chat further
and how can people contact you
so i'll leave my email another
information with you and then you can
share this with our viewers
thank you
we'll put some contact information in
the show notes
absolutely
thanks again venky this is a great
session i hope our listeners learned
from it just like i did
this is kanchan shrinky for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thank you very much i really love the
chat and hope to connect with our users
and learn more from them thank you
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
[Music]
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening